<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % local.common.attrib "xmlns:xi  CDATA  #FIXED 'http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude'">
]>
<chapter id="migrating-2-to-3">
  <title>Migrating from GNT 2.x to 3</title>

  <para>
    GNT 3 is a major new version of GNT that breaks both API and ABI compared
    to GNT 2.x. There are a number of steps that you can take to prepare your
    GNT 2.x application for the switch to GNT 3. After that, there's a small
    number of adjustments that you may have to do when you actually switch your
    application to build against GNT 3.
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>Preparation in GNT 2.x</title>

    <para>
      The steps outlined in the following sections assume that your application
      is working with GNT 2.14, which is the final stable release of GNT 2.x.
      It includes all the necessary APIs and tools to help you port your
      application to GNT 3. If you are still using an older version of GNT 2.x,
      you should first get your application to build and work with the latest
      minor release in the 2.14 series.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Do not use deprecated symbols</title>
      <para>
        Over the years, a number of functions have been deprecated. These
        deprecations are clearly spelled out in the API reference, with hints
        about the recommended replacements. The API reference for GNT 2 also
        includes an <ulink
          url="https://docs.pidgin.im/libgnt/next/api-deprecated.html">index of
        all deprecated symbols</ulink>.
      </para>
      <para>
        To verify that your program does not use any deprecated symbols, you
        can use preprocessor defines to remove deprecated symbols from the
        header files. As part of your compilation process, you may define the
        following:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <code>GNT_DISABLE_DEPRECATED</code> to hide deprecated symbols.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <code>GNTSEAL_ENABLE</code> to hide internal struct members.
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        Note that some parts of our API, such as enumeration values, are not
        well covered by the deprecation warnings. In most cases, using them
        will require you to also use deprecated functions, which will trigger
        warnings.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Changes that need to be done at the time of the switch</title>

    <para>
      This section outlines porting tasks that you need to tackle when you get
      to the point that you actually build your application against GNT 3.
      Making it possible to prepare for these in GNT 2 would have been either
      impossible or impractical.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Removed internal API</title>

      <para>
        The following tag names have been removed from the API entirely; use
        the name without the underscore instead:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><code>enum _GntFileType</code></listitem>
          <listitem><code>enum _GntMouseEvent</code></listitem>
          <listitem><code>enum _GntParamFlags</code></listitem>
          <listitem><code>enum _GntProgressBarOrientation</code></listitem>
          <listitem><code>enum _GntTreeColumnFlag</code></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        The following items were removed entirely:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <code>enum _GntKeyPressMode</code> and <code>GntKeyPressMode</code>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <code>enum _GntWidgetFlags</code> and <code>GntWidgetFlags</code>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Changed API</title>
      <para>
        The following items have been changed as part of the API break:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <code>ENTRY_CHAR</code> renamed to %GNT_ENTRY_CHAR
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <code>g_hash_table_duplicate</code> renamed to
            gnt_hash_table_duplicate()
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <code>GDupFunc</code> renamed to #GntDuplicateFunc
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <code>GntTreeHashFunc</code> removed in favor of #GHashFunc
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <code>GntTreeHashEqualityFunc</code> removed in favor of #GEqualFunc
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
